Markus Scharitzer



markus@scharitzer.io



+436605998730



linkedin.com/in/markus-scharitzer

Summary

As a Cloud Security Engineer and Architect Markus can draw from his 5 years of experience as a Security Manager and 8 years Linux System Engineer. My passion for cloud development led my the pursue a 3 year freelancing career as a cloud architect in my free time.

Experience



Cyber Security Manager/ITSO

Austro Control

Feb 2021 - Present (1 year 10 months +)

Led the projects to improve the security of the network architecture. Created secure system design guidelines. Conceputalized risk mitigations to physical and cybersecurity threats. Deputy to the Cybersecurity Expert Group within COOPANS. Led a team of 6 security engineers to deliver SOC capabilities such as threat assessments, incident response and vulnerability management. Built and drove metrics to report the board of directors.



Cloud & Cyber Security Architecture Consultant

Markus Scharitzer

Nov 2018 - Present (4 years 1 month +)

Freelance cloud security engineer and architect for startups and SMEs in the Vienna region. Built secure cloud environments on AWS for cloud native applications and workloads. Drove security through threat modelling for applications and networks. Validated security requirements for applications, networks and enterprises. Built and architected cloud native applications on AWS with Python.

Lecturer IT-Security

Fachhochschule Technikum Wien

Sep 2018 - Present (4 years 3 months +)

Teach and build a university course on Cloud Platforms, Architecture and Security for the Master's Degree in Software Engineering.

Teach and build a university course on Secure Software Development Life Cycle, Secure Systems Design, Security Architecture, SOC Capabilities and Analytic for the Master's Degree in Cyber Security



Senior Information Security Engineer

Austro Control

Mar 2019 - Feb 2021 (2 years)

Led the project & technical integration for a SIEM platform. Drove process development for incident handling & vulnerability management. Built security services & infrastructure. Developed software in Python & Go in order to create efficient services for vulnerability management and monitoring password security.

Team Lead IT Security Auditor

XSEC infosec GmbH

Mar 2018 - Oct 2018 (8 months)

Assessed the technical security of web stacks, from black box penetration test to source code audits in programming languages such as, but not only limited to, C# .NET and Java EE. Led a team of 4 to deliver quality reports and penetration testing services to our customers.

System & Security Administrator

Semantic Web Company (SWC)

May 2014 - Feb 2018 (3 years 10 months)

Drove the company wide security program, including policy writing, and technical implementation of counter measures, based on the ISO 27001 standard. Supported research and development activities with regards to operational aspects like reliability and scalability as well as security. Led administrator training for an international customer and partner base. Led a team of 3 to deliver modern infrastructure capabilities such as Infrastructure as Code, Identity Management and Cloud PoCs.



🦚 System Administrator & Software Developer

PRISMA solutions

Dec 2010 - Apr 2014 (3 years 5 months)

Implemented and validated custom backup solutions based on UNIX tools, spanning the whole infrastructure, including but not limited to networking gear, hypervisors, and applications. Administered various databases, PHP and JAVA applications and integrations to various data providers. Developed Software and Tools in Java, Python with RESTful APIs and IoT integrations.

Education

Fachhochschule Technikum Wien

Master of Science - MS, IT Security 2017 - 2019

Fachhochschule Technikum Wien

Bachelor of Science - BS, Information and Communication Systems and Services 2014 - 2017

Licenses & Certifications



Offensive Security Certified Professional OSCP - Offensive Security

OS-101-036174

Skills

Organizational Leadership • Critical Infrastructure Security • Cybersecurity • Cyber Defense • Software Architecture • System Architecture • Amazon Web Services (AWS) • Threat Modeling • Python (Programming Language) • Cloud Computing